#### **Muhammad Adnan Khalid**

Adnankhalid83@gmail.com Adnankhalid@hotmail.com

07544958979 Manchester UK







Senior Network & Security Engineer with 10 Years of experience within the fields of Network and Security with the ability to manage the projects with extensive Technical skills and synchronize the Network Infrastructure with Administration and Operational capabilities.

Comprehensive understanding of networking concepts pertaining to LAN, WAN, Security, Cloud and Data Centers in Multi-platform environments (Cisco, Fortinet, HP, F5, Palo Alto).

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

### **Vodafone Qatar**

### *IP & Security Engineer Feb 2017 – Present*

- Configuration and Management of IP and security infrastructure including Fortigate Firewalls, Cisco ASA, F5, Fortinet WEB, Manager, Analyzer, Omni switches and Alcatel Routers.
- Deployment, configuration and management of F5 Modules (LTM, CGNAT, PEM, AFM).
- Responsible for L2 and L3 operations and troubleshooting.
- Developing and reviewing technical documents including HLD, LLD, RCA, POC and Network Readiness/Handover.
- Technical team management for project deployment as per industry standard and best practices.
- Proactively identifies and nurtures opportunities, ideas and innovations required for the Network and Security Infrastructure.
- Involve in high severity troubleshooting in network security and designing.

#### **Qatar Datamation Systems**

## Senior Network and Security Engineer Oct 2015 – Jan 2017

- Responsible for planning and designing of Network and security infrastructure.
- Work with Presales and Design Consultant on the high-level design approval for various customer's projects.
- To fulfill the client requirement, prepare proposal, network designing, implementation and provide complete documentation including HLD and LLD and POC detail tasks.
- Troubleshooting and resolving network issues, as well as developing, applying and enforcing best practices and policies.
- Supervise, motivate and lead a team of Junior Engineers with KT sessions to ensuring optimum Operational performance.

## Responsible the deployment of following devices and technologies.

- Cisco ASA 5500 and 5585 Series Firewalls
- Cisco Nexus 7000 Switches
- Cisco WLC 2504, 5500 and 8500 Series Controllers
- Cisco ISE (Identity Services Engine) and ACS (Access Control Server)
- Cisco Email Security Appliance and Web Security Appliance
- Fortinet Security Solution includes (Foriwall, Web, Manager and Analyzer)
- Load Balancer F5 and Citrix NetScaler ADC
- HP Core Layer switches 10500 series and Wireless Controller.
- Fire Eye AMP Solution (NX, HX, EX)

#### SaldabIT AB Malmö Sweden

#### Network Consultant Jan 2014 - June 2015

- Managing and operating multi-vendor Network security infrastructure.
- Deployment of network infrastructure using firewall, routers and switches and wireless controllers and also provide 2nd and 3rd line support to the company's customers.
- Implement ZFS based network storage solution with Nappit as high-availability application.
- Implemented Fortigate unified threat management (UTM) using security profiles, Antivirus, Application Control, Intrusion Prevention (IPS) and Data Leak Prevention (DLP) with the best practice.
- Experience working with different vendor including Cisco business partners/system, integrator (Gold Partners) and Enterprise customers.
- Work with the various team members to develop/document the incident response procedures and compiling RCA reports.

#### Nordens Tekniska Institute YH Malmö Sweden

## Network Instructor Aug 2011 -- March 2013

Worked as a fulltime Instructor for Network Security and Administration program. Mainly focus on the following technologies.

- Routing and Switching
- Network Security
- Ethical hacking
- Penetration Testing
- VPN Technologies (IPsec, VTI, GRE, SSL).

Also responsible for coordination with IT companies to accomplished network Security projects.

#### InGate Systems AB Stockholm Sweden

## Network Engineer Nov 2010 -- May 2011

- Worked as a full-time Network Engineer and provide support to the company's internal infrastructure based on cisco and HP L2/L3 switches and Ingate Firewall.
- Installation and administration of Server's Infrastructure based on (Windows and Linux).
- Deployment of virtualized server platform using VMware ESXi Servers and managing Active Directory, DNS and request tracking system (RTS).
- Responsible for Designing and implementation of SIP Based VOIP Network with the integration of Ingate firewall.
- Dealing with the internal and external customer and provide L2/L3 support and documentation.

### Halmstad University Sweden

#### IT Lecturer Jan 2008-Nov 2009

Main responsibilities were teaching, conducting laboratory exercises and Supervision of Network Projects.

### **Courses:**

- Advanced Routing and Multilayer Switching
- Network Troubleshooting and QoS
- Linux administration
- Network Security
- Network Simulation

## **Certifications**

- CCIE Security (CCIE # 54731) 2016
- Certified Ethical Hacker V10 2019
- Fortinet NSE7 (Network Security Architect) -- 2018
- Fortinet NSE4 (Network Security Expert) 2017
- CCSP Security
- CCNA Routing and Switching
- CCNP Routing and switching
- Fortinet Certified Network Security Administrator (FCNSA.v5)
- Cisco R&S and Security Instructor
- Cisco Small and Midsize Business Engineer Representative
- HP Accredited Technical Professional (ATP)
- HP ASE Flex Network Integrator

# **Trainings**

- F5 Advance Technologies Deployment
- Certified Ethical Hacking v10

## **Education**

**Master in Computer Network Engineering** 

2008-2009

Halmstad University Sweden

Network Design and Computer Management 2006-2008

Halmstad University Sweden

**BS-Computer Science** 

2002-2005

University of Management and Technology

### **Research & Thesis**

Security Issues of Border Gateway Protocol in Complex Peering and Transit Networks at Halmstad University Sweden **2009**.

Deployment and implementation of virtual private networks in enterprise network with IPsec framework at UMT **2005.** 

### **Projects**

# BeinSports Doha 2015-16

- Implemented Fire eye AMP security solution based on their NX (fire eye network security appliance), EX (email security appliance) and HX (Endpoint security appliance) to protect the network, endpoints and Emails from Malwares and zero day attacks.
- Distributed deployment of (ISE) Identity service engine at beIN Sports Doha to provide network admission control for employees, contractors and guests.
- Configure authentication and authorization for clients based on all possible use cases (wired and wireless corporate PCs, wireless BYOD, Profiling based authorization for all Non dot1x devices (printers, cctv cameras, IPTV boxes, Access Points) for round about 1500 users.
- Guest access through self-registration guest portal and integrate ISE with SMS gateway to send login credential through SMS.
- Also Integrate ISE with Citrix XEN MDM (Mobile Device Management) to provide access to manage their devices through ISE Device Management Portal.
- Implement Email security appliance at beinsports Qatar to provide anti spamming and antimalware to protect mails from all the email threats and Integrated with the Threat grid appliance to provide the local sandboxing solution.

#### QNA Doha 2015-16

- Design and deployment of complete network infrastructure consists of Juniper firewalls cluster at perimeter and Fortinet firewalls in data center.
- Deploy and configure two tier HP switches at core and access layer based on IRF.
- Deployment of wireless solution based on HP MSM controller and Aps.
- Configure HA on the firewalls and IRF (Intelligent Resilience Framework) on the HP switches to provide high availability in the network.

### FingerPrint AB (Sweden) 2014-15

- Deploy and manage the network infrastructure based on Fortigate firewall, switches (Hp and cisco) and Forti Aps.
- Manage site to site VPNs between all the branches and HQ and SSL VPNs for remote clients.
- Implement fortigate Threat management solution includes security profiles based on antivirus, application control and data leak protection.
- Provide 24/7 maintenance support after deployment to troubleshoot network issues.

## Bassoe Tech (Sweden) 2014-15

- Implement network security and wireless solution for Bassoe Tech AB Sweden. Use 802.1x port based authentication to assign dynamic vlans for corporate and guest users.
- Manage site to site VPNs between all the branches and SSL VPN for all remote clients.
- Provide 24/7 maintenance support after deployment to troubleshoot network issues.

#### **Evedensia Nordic 2014-15**

- Evidensia is a Saldab's biggest customers in Sweden having branches all over the Nordic countries (Sweden, Denmark, Norway, and Finland).
- Connect all the branches through MPLS VPN to company's data center, implement routing switching, security and wireless based on fortigate products for all the branches.
- Design and Implement high availability solution and provide network redundancy solution based on MPLS and IPsec vpn to access the services in the datacenter.
- Implement end to end QoS solution for all sites of the customer for VoIP and critical business applications.
- Deployment of centralized based wireless solution for around 150 sites for all over the Nordic. Corporate access based on certificates and guest access based on captive portal.

## **Skills and Expertise**

Operating System: Microsoft (2008, 2012) and Linux (Red hat, Ubuntu) Servers. Switches and Routers: Cisco catalyst/Nexus, HP, 3com, Omni, Netgear, Alcatel. Firewalls: Fortinet, Cisco ASA, Palo Alto, Juniper, Dlink, Ingate, untangle, sophos

**Load Balancer:** F5, Citrix Netscaler

**Network Management**: Cisco Prime Infrastructure, PRTG Network Monitoring, Observium Network Monitoring, Solar wind Network Monitoring and Management, Cisco Access Control Server, Cisco ISE.

## **Personal**

DoB - 1983-sep-23 Languages - English, Swedish, Nationality - Swedish Driving License – Swedish, Qatar www.linkedin.com/in/khalidadnan